你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎收看PWN学院内核模块的第四个视频
welcome to the 4th video in the kernel module of pwn college
今天我们将讨论权限提升
today we're going to talk about privilege escalation
通常，如果在内核漏洞的背景下讨论权限提升
usually if we talk about privilege escalation in the context of kernel vulnerabilities
现在你将预览一下内核漏洞
you are going to get a preview of kernel vulnerabilities right now
但是在这个模块中
but in this module
主要是学习一下内核交互
you'll really learn how to interact with the kernel
理解
and understand
并在不涉及内核漏洞的情况下，与内核模块交互
and mess with kernel modules themselves without necessarily vulnerabilities
更像是逆向挑战题
more like reversing challenges let's say
但不难想象漏洞是如何发生的
but it's not hard to imagine how vulnerabilities can happen
每个内核模块都有两个非常重要的函数
there are two very important functions for every kernel module
一个函数将数据从内核空间复制到用户空间
one function copies data to user space from kernel space
另一个函数从内核空间复制数据
and other function copies data from kernel space
对不起
sorry
另一个是反方向的
another one goes the other way
一个函数，数据从内核到用户空间
so one from kernel space to user space
另一个，数据从用户空间到内核
and one from user space to kernel space
这些就像memcpy之类的
and these are like memcopies
就像任何memcpy类函数一样
and like any memcpy
就像任何内存数据传输功能一样
like any transfer memory
如果作者不细心
if authors aren't careful
就可能出现漏洞
vulnerabilities can arise
而且这确实经常发生
and in fact do arise very frequently
内核bug及其利用程序经常涌现
kernel bugs and their exploitations
漏洞的最大来源之一是
one of the biggest sources of exploitable vulnerabilities
例如Android内核
in the Android kernel for example
这很严重
it is a big deal
这不仅仅是内存破坏
and it's not just memory corruption
Linux内核中存在各种各样的漏洞
all sorts of vulnerability classes occur in the Linux kernel
就和内核外一样
just like they occur outside of the Linux kernel
假设你找到并要利用一个漏洞
so let's say you find and exploit this vulnerability
你能用它做什么呢
what can you do with it
经典的用途是提升正在运行的进程的特权
the classic is to elevate the privileges of your running process
内核记录着每个进程的特权
every process has its privileges tracked by the kernel
内核通过task_struct记录了一大堆信息
the kernel tracks a task struct with a whole lot of info
包括调度优先级
including scheduling priority
各种各样的东西
all sorts of stuff
其中之一是
but one of the things that it stores is
进程的凭据
the credentials of the process
它存储在cred结构体中
and this is stored in a cred struct
cred结构体中有
and the cred struct has among other things
进程的euid
the effective user id of that process
如果你把它改成0
and if you overwrite that with zero
你就是root了
you are root
因为root的uid是0
because root has a uid of zero
这就是你的目标
so that's your goal
要提权
to escalate your privileges
你可以将自己的uid改成0
you can overwrite your uid with zero
就好了
and you're good to go
除非系统开启了别的东西
unless there's some other stuff going on
比如seccomp等等
like seccomp and so forth
我们以后会讨论如何逃逸seccomp
we'll talk about how to escape that in
等到我们把这个概念和越狱结合起来
when we put this concept together with jailbreaking
但先把重点放在提权到euid为root上
but for now let's focus on elevating your process's privileges to an effective user id of root
实际上
it turns out
不用在内存中翻找这个结构体，然后改这个字段
it's actually easier than crawling through memory to find a field in a structure and override it
内核提供了两个很好的api
the kernel provides two very nice apis
一个能把当前cred结构体对象替换成别的
one of them replaces our cred struct with some other cred struct
另一个
and the other one
能为我们创建一个cred结构体对象
can create a cred struct for us
就是这个prepare_kernel_cred
this prepare_kernel_cred
如果你给它传一个null
if you pass it a null
给它传一个0作为参数
pass it a zero as the argument
它会创建一个cred结构体对象
it will actually create a cred struct
代表一个root创建的新会话
representing a new session created by root
不受任何非root权限的污染等等
untainted of any non root privileges and so forth
很好
it's great
所以如果传入0，它就创建一个全0的对象
so prepare_kernel_cred will create this structure with all zeros where if you pass a zero
再commit_creds启用它
and then commit_creds will set it as the cred structure of our struct
所以我们只要执行
and so all we have to run
为了获得root权限
in order to achieve root access
前提是我们能在内核中执行代码
once we have code execution in the kernel
只要执行它
is this
我们来看看如何做到这一点
let's take a look at how we can do that
我准备了一个示例模块
i actually have a demo module for us
这个示例模块在pwnkernel中
and that demo module is in pwnkernel
它是make_root.c
and it is make_root.c
它是一个非常简单的模块
it's a very simple module
它在/proc下创建一个设备文件
it creates a device in /proc
是/proc/pwn.college-root
it's ?? /proc/pwn.college-root
它为该设备文件注册了一堆操作函数
it registers a bunch of operations for that device
一眼能看到读和写的
you can see immediately read and write
它们什么都不做
they don't do anything
它们就返回一个无效参数
they just return a invalid argument
EINVAL
它注册了这个ioctl处理程序
and it registers this ioctl handler
这个ioctl处理程序
and then the ioctl handler
我们可以看到
we can see that
如果我们ioctl_num传的PWN
if we used an ioctl_num of PWN
PWN定义在这里
and PWN is defined up here
我们马上就会知道它是多少
and we'll figure out what it is in a second
它是一个宏定义的数
it's some macro defined number
另一个参数为13371337
and a parameter of 13371337
它会打一条日志，说要给我们root权限
it will log that it's granting us root access
然后给我们root权限
and then grant us root access
这太棒了
this is great
我们要创建一个程序
so we need to create a program
因为这要在程序中完成
because this will need to be done from inside a program
我们要创建一个程序，它会open这个文件
we need to create a program that opens this file
/proc/pwn.college-root
然后用正确的ioctl_num和参数，触发ioctl处理程序
and triggers the ioctl with the correct ioctl number and the correct ioctl parameter
然后这个进程就会神奇地变成root
and then that process will magically become root
非常令人兴奋
it's very exciting
我们来写这个程序
so let's write it
写这里吧
actually let's write it here
好的
okay
首先
so first of all
我们要打开/proc
we want to open proc
我们先启动这个内核，确保文件名正确
let's launch this and make sure that we have the file name correct
好的
okay
加载这个模块
we have this loaded
这个设备文件在这
here it is
我们以只读模式打开它
so we're gonna open this in read only mode
然后我们调用ioctl
and we are going to run our ioctl
我们断言，fd大于0
let's actually assert that fd is greater than 0
确保能正常打开文件
that it opened correctly
为此需要包含assert.h
need to include assert.h for this
好的
okay
我们用这个文件描述符，还有一些参数
we run ioctl on that file descriptor with some parameter
我们不知道这里是什么
we don't know what this is
这里是PWN
this is PWN
我们要逆向内核模块来找出它
we'll need to reverse engineer the kernel module to understand what it is
还有0x13371337
and 0x13371337
然后
and then
我们就应该是root了
we should be root
然后我们输出
so then we wanted to printf
执行ioctl前也输出一下
let's do the same thing for before
好的，我们看看会发生什么
okay let's see what happens
执行前，它应该就是开始的用户
so before it should be whatever user we start out as
执行后，一切正常的话
after if we did everything right
这应该是root
this should be root
我们以静态链接的方式编译它
we want to compile this statically
这个小系统中，没有动态链接库
again there are no libraries in our minimized system here
当然这里没定义PWN
of course PWN is undeclared
我们来找一下它是多少
so let's figure out what that is
这是我们的内核模块
so we have our kernel module
它实际上编译到这里了
it is actually compiled in here
make_root.ko
这是我们的内核模块本身
this is our the kernel module itself
它只是个elf文件
it's just an elf
这意味着你可以objdump -d它
that means you can objdump -d it
或用binary ninja或其他工具打开它
or open it up in binary ninja or any other tool
如果我们看看device_ioctl
and if we look at device_ioctl
我们看到它与7001比较
we see that it compares against 7001
用ebx比的
and compares ebx
ebx来自esi
ebx comes from esi
esi是第二个参数
esi is the second argument
欧了，7001就是我们需要的
boom 7001 is what we need
编译
compile
现在就好了
now it worked
这是我们的attack
there's our attack
现在我们切到ctf用户
so now let's become the ctf user
现在我们是ctf用户
now we're the ctf user
当然
of course
ctf主目录挂载了系统的主目录
ctf home directory has my home directory of my system mounted
attck在这儿
here it is attack
之前是1000，之后是0
before 1000 after 0
特权升级了
privilege escalation
所以
so
我们快速看一下我们可以用它做什么
let's take a look real quick at what we can do with this
显然，在此之后，我们可以读取flag
obviously after this we can read out the flag file
或者我们用execl
or we use the execl
一个libc函数，封装了execve
a libc function to wrap around execve
来执行/bin/sh
to execute /bin/sh
因为prepare_cred_struct(0)
since prepare_cred_struct null
创造了一个
creates an authentic of a full
一切都是零
everything is zeros
ruid是0
the real user id
euid是0
the effective user id
所以/bin/sh可以正常工作
/bin/sh works just fine
特权不会降低
it won't drop privileges
这是argv
so this is argv
这是要运行的二进制文件
this is the binary to run
这是参数0
this is argv 1 argv 0 sorry
参数1是null
argv 1 is null
就是启动一个/bin/sh
just runs /bin/sh
编译
compile
运行
run
成了
boom
我们拿到了flag
we got the flag
好了
there we go
我们看了这个make_root.c模块
we looked at this make_root.c module
找到了触发这种情况的方法
and figured out how to trigger this condition
写了一个attack.c
and wrote an attack.c
它触发了这个情况
that triggers the condition
调用了，使用ioctl
calls causes using this ioctl
使commit_creds(prepare_kernel_cred(0))被调用了
the commit_cred prepare_cred to be called
就成了
and boom
你可以想象
you can imagine
你将来可能会在内核中触发内存破坏
that you might in the future trigger memory corruption in the kernel
注入调用这个的代码
and be able to inject code that calls this
那么有哪些注意事项呢
so what are some complications
好吧
well
如果你要在shellcode中调用这两个函数
if you have to provide shellcode for example that triggers this
你需要知道
you need to understand
commit_creds和prepare_kernel_cred在内存的哪里
where commit_cred and prepare_kernel_cred is in memory
现代内核默认启用了ASLR
modern kernels with default settings have ASLR
叫KASLR
it's called KASLR
内核中的ASLR
ASLR in the kernel
所以它们不会被映射到可预测的位置
and so they won't be mapped at predictable locations
但这里的题目中关闭了KASLR
but these intro challenges have KASLR disabled
还有老的内核
and older kernels
例如，许多嵌入式设备也禁用了KASLR
such as many of those embedded devices have KASLR disabled as well
有一个文件叫做/proc/kallsyms
and there's a file called /proc/kallsyms
实际上，大多数情况都没它的访问权限
it is realistically mostly blocked off
除非你有root权限
unless you have root access
但这取决于具体情况
but depending on the scenario
你可能有root访问权限
you might have root access
并在攻击内核
and be attacking the kernel
/proc/kallsyms有所有符号的地址
/proc/kallsyms has the locations of all of the symbols
内核中的所有函数
all the functions in the kernel
包括我们刚刚加载的模块
including actually our module that we just loaded
这很酷
which is really cool
我们找一下prepare_kernel_cred
but let's grep for prepare_kernel_cred
在这儿
boom there
这是prepare_kernel_cred的地址
that's the address of prepare_kernel_cred
这是commit_cred的地址
and that's the address of commit_cred
剩下的你们就知道了
and the rest you know
你知道该怎么做
you know how to do
你在用户空间都做过了
you have done this in user space
内核空间并没有那么特殊
kernel space is not that special
另外，我还展示过了如何调试内核
otherwise i showed you how to debug kernel
如果你开启了调试选项
so if you have debugging enabled
在qemu中开启
you know in qemu
你可以附加进来，并搜索内存
you can attach and search around memory and so forth
否则，你需要一个信息泄露漏洞
otherwise you will need a leak
这和用户空间aslr的一样
it's the same problem as user space aslr
事实上
in fact on this note
内核有很多针对攻击的保护机制
the kernel has a lot of mitigations against attacks
我们将在以后的模块中讨论这些
and we'll talk about those in a future module
等我们把这些都放到一起
when we talk about putting together
所有你知道并掌握的漏洞
all of the vulnerability classes that you know and have mastered
以及内核空间中的操作
together with operations in kernel space
在我们的第二个组合模块 toddler2 中
in our second putting it all together module toddler 2
在那之前
until then
好好享受这个内核介绍模块吧
enjoy these introductory kernel modules
我们尽量减轻你的负担
we try to give you a lighter load with them
希望我们成功了
hopefully we succeeded
并且你可以专注于理解内核
and you can focus on truly understanding the kernel
以及如何与之互动
and how to interact with it
祝你好运
good luck